<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-12-20T20:16:30-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/index.xml</id><title type="html">Adrian does A.I.</title><subtitle>Software, IT, Hardware, Networking, A.I. Chat Bot, A.I. Automation, Professional Portfolio, Web Development, Machine Learning, Web Scraping, Data Collection in Portland, Oregon or Remote - Adrian Hacker</subtitle><entry><title type="html">DIY Smart Home and Cloud Storage</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/self-hosting" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="DIY Smart Home and Cloud Storage" /><published>2023-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-12-15T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/self-hosting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/self-hosting"><![CDATA[<h2 id="why-even-bother-with-your-own-cloud">Why even bother with your own cloud?</h2>
<p>Smart home devices and the Internet of Things (IoT) are revolutionizing our daily lives. Commands like “Alexa, do this…” and “OK Google, do that” have become commonplace, managing everything from lighting to thermostats and cameras. However, these connected devices often lack regular software updates – a fact that makes them prime targets for attackers looking to infiltrate home networks. Moreover, with devices like Alexa always listening and services like Gmail limiting storage unless you subscribe for more, there’s a growing concern about privacy and data management. This has led me to decide to convert my online presence entirely to self-hosted solutions.</p>

<h2 id="risky-devices">Risky Devices</h2>
<p>The University of Texas at San Antonio has <a href="https://cias.utsa.edu/hackers-can-hijack-your-home-with-these-10-smart-devices/">Identified 10 smart devices</a> that put your home network at risk:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Wireless Laptops</li>
  <li>Online Gaming Systems</li>
  <li>Webcams</li>
  <li>Home Wireless Network / Router</li>
  <li>Smart Lightbulbs</li>
  <li>Smart TV’s</li>
  <li>Coffee Makers</li>
  <li>Smart Phones</li>
  <li>Smart Refrigerators</li>
  <li>Portable Radios</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="signs-of-a-hacked-home-network">Signs of a Hacked Home Network</h2>
<p>I have been hacked one time, but it did not affect my entire network and it was really my fault because I was trying to install shady pirated software that was allegedly jail broken.  I got what I deserved.  I have been fortunate enough to avoid an entire hacked home network, but Norton identified ten signs that <a href="https://us.norton.com/blog/privacy/how-to-tell-if-someone-hacked-your-router">your network could be hacked:</a></p>

<ul>
  <li>Sudden inability to login to your routers default admin</li>
  <li>Slow internet speeds</li>
  <li>Browser redirects</li>
  <li>Suspicious network activity</li>
  <li>Unfamiliar software downloads</li>
  <li>Session hijacking</li>
  <li>Ransomeware messages</li>
  <li>Fake antivirus notifications</li>
  <li>Increase in pop-up advertisements</li>
  <li>Alerts from your internet provider</li>
</ul>

<p>If you are a Windows user, this does not mean sit and look at your processes and programs that are running.  That is always enough to sketch a poor soul out, and that is because there are so many background things running.  If in doubt, Google it.</p>

<h2 id="the-promise-of-enhanced-privacy-and-control">The Promise of Enhanced Privacy and Control</h2>
<p>In contrast to mainstream services, self-hosting offers unparalleled privacy. By managing your data on a private network, you significantly reduce the risk of external breaches and surveillance. This approach not only protects your information from unauthorized access but also keeps it away from the prying eyes of large corporations.</p>

<h2 id="the-sovereignty-of-your-data">The Sovereignty of Your Data</h2>
<p>With self-hosting, your data remains under your control, subject only to your country’s laws. This is in stark contrast to storing data on servers across borders, where it may be subject to foreign surveillance and regulations. This level of data sovereignty is particularly crucial in a world where digital boundaries are increasingly blurred.</p>

<h2 id="steering-clear-of-subscription-fatigue">Steering Clear of Subscription Fatigue</h2>
<p>The growing trend of subscription-based models for cloud storage and smart home features can be financially draining. Self-hosting, on the other hand, involves a one-time setup cost, potentially saving money in the long term by eliminating recurring fees.</p>

<h2 id="customization-at-your-fingertips">Customization at Your Fingertips</h2>
<p>One of the most significant advantages of self-hosting is the ability to tailor your systems exactly to your needs. Unlike being restricted to the features and integrations of mainstream providers, self-hosting allows for a more personalized and independent setup.</p>

<h2 id="a-fortified-digital-fortress">A Fortified Digital Fortress</h2>
<p>Mainstream cloud services and IoT devices are often targets for cybercriminals. By self-hosting, your system becomes less attractive to hackers. Moreover, you have the freedom to implement robust security measures that align with your comfort level, further fortifying your digital domain.</p>

<h2 id="always-accessible-internet-or-not">Always Accessible, Internet or Not</h2>
<p>Another notable benefit of self-hosting is the ability to access your data locally, without an internet connection. This ensures that you have uninterrupted access to your information, even during internet outages, a feature often overlooked in mainstream cloud services.</p>

<h2 id="empowerment-through-learning">Empowerment Through Learning</h2>
<p>Embarking on the journey of setting up and maintaining a self-hosted system is not only about gaining control over your data; it’s also an opportunity for substantial skill development. It immerses you in the realms of networking, cybersecurity, and system administration, enhancing your technical acumen.</p>

<h2 id="embracing-the-challenges">Embracing the Challenges</h2>
<p>Despite its many advantages, self-hosting is not without its challenges. It requires a certain level of technical expertise, a commitment to ongoing maintenance, and an upfront investment in time and resources. However, for those who value their digital privacy and autonomy, these challenges are a small price to pay for the peace of mind and control that self-hosting provides.</p>

<h2 id="the-phases">The Phases</h2>

<p>This process will be divided into certain phases and I will keep a badge on my site that has the quick and dirty about where I am at with this.  The phases will be:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Planning:  A written plan regarding the hardware and software to be used.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Construction:  Building and installing the decided solutions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Evaluation:  Evaluating the build to provide some reviews and recommendations for varying features and skill levels.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Report: Final post of all details in this home server iteration.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>A server must be set up, then the smart devices must be set up.  I will also have updates as the process goes.  This is being done as finance permits, so it might not be overnight.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, transitioning to self-hosted cloud storage and smart home devices is a powerful step towards reclaiming your digital privacy and independence. While it demands effort and technical know-how, the benefits of enhanced privacy, data sovereignty, and personalization make it a compelling choice for those concerned about their digital footprint in the increasingly interconnected world of IoT.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian Hacker</name></author><category term="Privacy" /><category term="cloud," /><category term="self-hosted," /><category term="storage," /><category term="smart" /><category term="home," /><category term="alexa," /><category term="google" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why even bother with your own cloud? Smart home devices and the Internet of Things (IoT) are revolutionizing our daily lives. Commands like “Alexa, do this…” and “OK Google, do that” have become commonplace, managing everything from lighting to thermostats and cameras. However, these connected devices often lack regular software updates – a fact that makes them prime targets for attackers looking to infiltrate home networks. Moreover, with devices like Alexa always listening and services like Gmail limiting storage unless you subscribe for more, there’s a growing concern about privacy and data management. This has led me to decide to convert my online presence entirely to self-hosted solutions.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Blockchain Basics: How Does It Work?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blockchain-explainer" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Blockchain Basics: How Does It Work?" /><published>2023-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blockchain-explainer</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blockchain-explainer"><![CDATA[<h1 id="understanding-blockchain-basics-how-does-it-work">Understanding Blockchain Basics: How Does It Work?</h1>

<p><img src="https://images.unsplash.com/photo-1639322537228-f710d846310a?auto=format%2Ccompress&amp;fm=webp&amp;fit=crop&amp;crop=faces%2Cedges&amp;w=1200&amp;h=675&amp;q=60&amp;cs=tinysrgb" alt="Understanding Blockchain Basics: How Does It Work?" /></p>

<h2 id="exploring-blockchain-technology">Exploring Blockchain Technology</h2>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blockchain">Blockchain</a> technology has emerged as a groundbreaking innovation with the potential to revolutionize various industries. In this blog, we will provide an overview of blockchain technology and delve into its inner workings. By understanding the fundamentals of blockchain, you will gain insights into how this technology operates and its transformative capabilities.</p>

<p>Blockchain technology is often referred to as a distributed ledger that records transactions across multiple computers or nodes. It eliminates the need for intermediaries, such as banks or governments, by enabling direct peer-to-peer transactions. This decentralized nature ensures transparency, security, and immutability in data management.</p>

<p>Throughout this blog, we will explore the key principles behind blockchain technology, including <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decentralization">decentralization</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cryptography">cryptography</a>. We will also discuss the concept of blocks and chains that form the foundation of blockchain architecture. By the end of this article, you will have a comprehensive understanding of how blockchain works and its potential applications in various sectors.</p>

<h2 id="the-power-of-decentralization-and-cryptography">The Power of Decentralization and Cryptography</h2>

<h3 id="decentralization-redefining-trust">Decentralization: Redefining Trust</h3>

<p>Decentralization lies at the core of blockchain technology, redefining the way trust is established and maintained in digital transactions. Unlike traditional systems that rely on centralized authorities, blockchain eliminates the need for intermediaries by enabling direct peer-to-peer transactions.</p>

<p>By distributing transaction records across a network of computers or nodes, blockchain ensures transparency and immutability. Each participant in the network has access to a copy of the entire blockchain, making it nearly impossible to alter or manipulate data without consensus from the majority.</p>

<p>This decentralized nature brings several advantages. It reduces dependency on centralized entities, mitigates single points of failure, and enhances security by eliminating vulnerabilities associated with central control. Blockchain’s decentralized architecture empowers individuals and organizations to transact directly with each other, fostering greater autonomy and efficiency.</p>

<h3 id="cryptography-securing-data-and-transactions">Cryptography: Securing Data and Transactions</h3>

<p>Cryptography plays a vital role in securing data and transactions within the blockchain ecosystem. It involves using mathematical algorithms to encrypt information, ensuring its confidentiality, integrity, and authenticity.</p>

<p>Public and private key encryption is a fundamental aspect of blockchain cryptography. Each participant in the network <a href="None">pos</a>sesses a unique pair of cryptographic keys: a public key for identification and a private key for authentication. When initiating a transaction, the sender uses their private key to create a digital signature that verifies their identity. The recipient can then use the sender’s public key to validate the signature and ensure the transaction’s integrity.</p>

<p>The use of cryptography in blockchain technology provides robust security measures against unauthorized access or tampering. It enables participants to have full control over their digital assets while maintaining privacy and protecting sensitive information.</p>

<h2 id="blocks-and-chains-the-building-blocks-of-blockchain">Blocks and Chains: The Building Blocks of Blockchain</h2>

<h3 id="blocks-storing-information">Blocks: Storing Information</h3>

<p>Blocks are the fundamental units that store information within a blockchain. Each block contains a set of data, such as transaction details, timestamps, and other relevant information. These blocks are linked together in a chronological order, forming a chain-like structure.</p>

<p>One crucial element of each block is its unique identifier called a hash. A hash is a cryptographic function that converts the data within a block into a fixed-length string of characters. This hash serves as a digital fingerprint for the block, ensuring its integrity and preventing any modifications to its contents.</p>

<p>The linking of blocks creates an immutable record of transactions or events on the blockchain. As new transactions occur, they are added to the latest block in the chain. This sequential arrangement ensures transparency and traceability since every transaction can be traced back to its respective block.</p>

<h3 id="chains-ensuring-consensus">Chains: Ensuring Consensus</h3>

<p>Chains connect individual blocks within the blockchain and play a vital role in maintaining consensus among participants. Consensus mechanisms, such as proof-of-work (<a href="None">PoW</a>) or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proof_of_stake">proof-of-stake</a> (PoS), are employed to validate transactions and ensure agreement across the network.</p>

<p>In proof-of-work systems like <a href="None">Bitcoin</a>, miners compete to solve complex mathematical puzzles to add new blocks to the chain. Once solved, these miners broadcast their solution to the network for verification by other participants. If consensus is reached that the solution is valid, the new block is added to the chain.</p>

<p>Proof-of-stake mechanisms work differently by allowing participants who hold a certain amount of cryptocurrency to create new blocks based on their stake or ownership. This approach reduces energy consumption compared to PoW systems while still maintaining security and consensus.</p>

<p>By utilizing chains and consensus mechanisms, blockchain technology enables trustless transactions without relying on centralized authorities or intermediaries.</p>

<h2 id="unlocking-the-potential-blockchain-applications-and-benefits">Unlocking the Potential: Blockchain Applications and Benefits</h2>

<h3 id="secure-and-transparent-transactions">Secure and Transparent Transactions</h3>

<p>One of the key advantages of blockchain technology is its ability to ensure secure and tamper-proof transactions. By utilizing cryptographic techniques, blockchain provides a high level of security, making it extremely difficult for unauthorized parties to alter or manipulate transaction data.</p>

<p>Additionally, blockchain offers transparency in transactions. Every transaction recorded on the blockchain is visible to all participants in the network. This transparency allows for traceability and accountability, as each transaction can be traced back to its origin. It also reduces the risk of fraud since any suspicious activity can be easily identified and investigated.</p>

<h3 id="supply-chain-management">Supply Chain Management</h3>

<p>Blockchain has significant implications for supply chain management. By leveraging its decentralized and transparent nature, blockchain improves supply chain efficiency while reducing fraud and counterfeiting.</p>

<p>With blockchain, supply chain participants can track goods in real-time throughout their journey from production to delivery. Each step is recorded on the blockchain, providing an immutable record of every interaction or event along the way. This enables enhanced visibility into the supply chain, allowing stakeholders to identify bottlenecks, optimize processes, and ensure compliance with regulations.</p>

<p>Moreover, blockchain enables verification of product authenticity by securely storing information about each item’s origin, manufacturing process, and distribution history. This helps combat counterfeit products by ensuring that consumers receive genuine goods.</p>

<p>The benefits of using blockchain in supply chain management extend beyond efficiency gains. It fosters trust among participants by providing a shared source of truth that cannot be easily manipulated or disputed. This trust-building aspect enhances collaboration between different entities within the supply chain ecosystem.</p>

<h2 id="overcoming-challenges-and-future-prospects">Overcoming Challenges and Future Prospects</h2>

<h3 id="scalability-and-energy-consumption">Scalability and Energy Consumption</h3>

<p>While blockchain technology offers numerous benefits, it also faces challenges that need to be addressed for widespread adoption. One of the primary challenges is scalability. As more transactions are added to the blockchain, the network can become congested, leading to slower transaction processing times. This issue becomes particularly relevant in public blockchains with a large number of participants.</p>

<p>Energy consumption is another concern associated with blockchain technology, especially in proof-of-work (PoW) blockchains like Bitcoin. The PoW consensus mechanism requires significant computational power, resulting in high energy consumption. This has raised environmental concerns and calls for more energy-efficient alternatives.</p>

<p>Efforts are underway to address these challenges. Various scaling solutions such as sharding and layer-two protocols aim to improve blockchain’s capacity to handle a higher volume of transactions without sacrificing security or decentralization. Additionally, alternative consensus mechanisms like proof-of-stake (PoS) offer a more energy-efficient approach by requiring participants to hold and lock up cryptocurrency as collateral instead of relying on computational work.</p>

<h3 id="future-applications-in-healthcare-and-voting-systems">Future Applications in Healthcare and Voting Systems</h3>

<p>Blockchain holds immense potential for transforming industries beyond finance. In healthcare, blockchain technology can revolutionize data management by providing secure and interoperable systems for storing and sharing patient records. It enables patients to have control over their health data while ensuring privacy and facilitating seamless information exchange between healthcare providers.</p>

<p>Voting systems can also benefit from blockchain’s properties of transparency, immutability, and security. By leveraging blockchain technology, voting processes can become more efficient, resistant to fraud, and transparent. Blockchain-based voting systems have the potential to enhance trust in democratic processes by enabling verifiable elections that cannot be tampered with or manipulated.</p>

<p>As blockchain continues to evolve, its applications are expected to expand into various other sectors such as supply chain management, intellectual property rights protection, decentralized finance (<a href="None">DeFi</a>), and more. The transformative potential of blockchain technology is vast, and its impact on industries and society as a whole is yet to be fully realized.</p>

<h2 id="embracing-the-future-the-transformative-potential-of-blockchain">Embracing the Future: The Transformative Potential of Blockchain</h2>

<p>Blockchain technology has emerged as a powerful force with the potential to revolutionize various industries. Its secure and transparent nature opens up new possibilities for innovation, transforming the way we conduct transactions, manage data, and establish trust.</p>

<p>By understanding blockchain’s fundamentals and how it works, we can unlock its transformative potential. From secure and tamper-proof transactions to efficient supply chain management, blockchain offers numerous benefits that can enhance transparency, accountability, and efficiency across various sectors.</p>

<p>As blockchain continues to evolve and overcome challenges such as scalability and energy consumption, its future prospects are promising. Industries like healthcare and voting systems stand to benefit greatly from blockchain’s ability to improve data management, enhance security, and foster trust.</p>

<p>Embracing blockchain technology means embracing a future where decentralized systems redefine trust, enable peer-to-peer interactions, and drive innovation across multiple domains. By harnessing the power of blockchain, we pave the way for a more secure, transparent, and efficient digital ecosystem.</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian Hacker</name></author><category term="Blockchain" /><category term="blockchain," /><category term="cryptocurrency," /><category term="cryptography," /><category term="crypto," /><category term="block" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding Blockchain Basics: How Does It Work?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About Firing Sam Altman from OpenAI</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/sam-altman" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Firing Sam Altman from OpenAI" /><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/sam-altman</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/sam-altman"><![CDATA[<h1>About Firing Sam Altman from OpenAI</h1>
<p>Dear "The Board of Directors at OpenAI",</p>
<p>There are only two CEO's in the entire world that I am familiar with.  The first one happens to run a car company, a space company, and X (formerly Twitter).</p>
<p>The second one is Sam Altman.  Practically the face of A.I. for most people.  Did no one ask chatGPT's opinion about this one, because I think the decision would have gone differently if that were the case.</p>
<p>Oopsies on you.</p>
<p>Love, Adrian</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian Hacker</name></author><category term="Artificial Intelligence" /><category term="a.i.," /><category term="sam" /><category term="altman," /><category term="OpenAI" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[About Firing Sam Altman from OpenAI Dear "The Board of Directors at OpenAI", There are only two CEO's in the entire world that I am familiar with. The first one happens to run a car company, a space company, and X (formerly Twitter). The second one is Sam Altman. Practically the face of A.I. for most people. Did no one ask chatGPT's opinion about this one, because I think the decision would have gone differently if that were the case. Oopsies on you. Love, Adrian]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why You Don’t Have to Fear A.I.</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/wanda-wont-ai" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why You Don’t Have to Fear A.I." /><published>2023-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-18T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/wanda-wont-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/wanda-wont-ai"><![CDATA[<h1>Wanda Won't A.I.</h1>
<p>Unofficially, this blog post is titled "Wanda Won't A.I." and it refers to my beautiful calico kitty who, if she were a person, I know would loathe the idea of artificial intelligence. Just as the robot vacuum has evolved to scare Wanda more thoroughly, so too has technology evolved to make people frightened. Enter: Artificial Intelligence. Perhaps the Matrix or Terminator 2 are plausible scenarios on the horizon people are wondering about. No, both A.I. and the robot vacuum are just two different facets of technology that is much older than people realize. And equally as harmless (mostly). Some interesting parallels exist in history around general fears of new technology.</p>

<h2>Some History of Technology and Fear</h2>
<ul>
<li>
The Locomotive – "Faster Than a Speeding Horse!" (Early 19th Century): When the first steam locomotives chugged onto the scene, people were terrified. They thought traveling at speeds of over 30 mph would cause the human body to melt! Imagine that – "Honey, I'm just off to melt on the 8:15 to Manchester."
</li>

<li>
The Telegraph – "Wires of Witchcraft!" (Mid-19th Century): The telegraph was basically the WhatsApp of the 1800s. But, not everyone was thrilled. Some thought these invisible messages sent through wires were the work of dark forces. "Beware the witchcraft that sends words without wings!"
</li>

<li>
The Telephone – "The Devil's Instrument" (Late 19th Century): When Alexander Graham Bell's invention started connecting people, some feared it was an instrument of evil. There were concerns about electricity's potential to carry voices of the dead. "Hello, is it me you're looking for?" might have had a whole different meaning back then.
</li>

<li>
Electricity – "It's Electrifying, and Terrifying!" (Late 19th Century): The introduction of electricity into homes was met with skepticism and fear. People were worried about being electrocuted by light switches. "Turn on the light? I'd rather not dance with death today, thank you."
</li>

<li>
The Automobile – "Horseless Madness!" (Early 20th Century): The early cars were seen as noisy, smelly, and dangerous beasts compared to the trusty horse. There were even laws requiring a person to walk in front of a car waving a red flag. "Beware, the horseless carriage cometh!"
</li>
</ul>

<h2>Balancing Act: Navigating the Cat-and-Mouse Game with A.I.</h2>
<p>In the world of technology, as in the world of cats, a delicate balancing act often unfolds. Just as a cat teeters between curiosity and caution when investigating a new object, we find ourselves navigating the intricate relationship between the risks and rewards of artificial intelligence (AI).</p>

<h3>Understanding the Risks</h3>
<p>Just as we wouldn't want our adventurous feline friends to dart into danger, it's crucial to acknowledge the potential risks associated with AI. Some concerns include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Loss of Control: Allowing AI systems to make critical decisions without human oversight can be risky. Just as we guide our cats away from harm, we must maintain control over AI's actions.
</li>
<li>
Deepfakes and Misinformation: AI's ability to generate convincing deepfakes and spread misinformation can be concerning. Like deciphering a cat's intentions, it can be challenging to discern truth from fiction.
</li>
<li>
Bias and Discrimination: AI algorithms can inherit biases present in their training data, leading to discriminatory outcomes. Just as we strive for fairness and equality, we must ensure AI systems do the same.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>Embracing the Rewards</h3>
<p>Much like when a cat finally pounces and captures its elusive prey, there are rewarding aspects to embracing AI:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Problem-Solving: AI can tackle complex problems that were once beyond our grasp. Just as a cat's patience pays off during a stealthy hunt, AI's problem-solving capabilities can lead to breakthroughs in various domains.
</li>
<li>
Enhanced Quality of Life: AI-driven innovations can enhance our daily lives, from smart homes that adjust to our preferences to personalized medical treatments. Just as a cat seeks comfort and convenience, AI strives to provide the same.
</li>
<li>
Innovation and Progress: Just as cats adapt to their ever-changing environment, embracing AI can drive innovation and progress in our rapidly evolving world. AI is the catalyst for groundbreaking discoveries and technological advancements.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>Striking the Balance</h3>
<p>So, how do we strike the right balance between the risks and rewards of AI? Much like observing a cat's behavior to ensure their safety, here are some strategies:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Ethical Guidelines: Establish clear ethical guidelines for AI development and usage to mitigate potential risks and ensure responsible AI practices.
</li>
<li>
Oversight and Accountability: Maintain human oversight over AI systems to prevent unintended consequences and hold individuals and organizations accountable for AI-related actions.
</li>
<li>
Education and Awareness: Educate ourselves about AI to better understand its capabilities and limitations, enabling us to make informed decisions.
</li>
</ul>

<h2>What is Machine Learning Anyway? Machine Learning Explained</h2>
<p>Machine learning can be broken down into two different types: Supervised and Unsupervised Learning.</p>

<h3>Supervised Learning: "Math as a Pattern Detective"</h3>
<p>In supervised learning, think of mathematics as a detective solving a puzzle. The puzzle is to find a function (a mathematical model) that best describes the relationship between input data (features) and output data (labels).</p>
<ul>
<li>
Data: Labeled data (e.g., pictures of cats and dogs with "cat" or "dog" labels).
</li>
<li>
Mathematics at Work:
<ul>
<li>
Statistical Analysis: It starts with statistical methods to understand data features.
</li>
<li>
Function Approximation: The core task is to approximate a function (think of it like y = f(x)) that can predict the output (y) for a new input (x).
</li>
<li>
Optimization: Algorithms like gradient descent are used to minimize errors in predictions.
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
Goal: To create a mathematical model that can accurately predict the label for new, unseen data.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>Unsupervised Learning: "Math as a Pattern Explorer"</h3>
<p>In unsupervised learning, mathematics is like an explorer trying to map out an unknown territory. The goal is to explore data and find some inherent structure or patterns without any predefined labels.</p>
<ul>
<li>
Data: Unlabeled data (like a mix of different objects).
</li>
<li>
Mathematics at Work: 
<ul>
<li>
Clustering Algorithms: Methods like K-means clustering where the algorithm tries to group data into clusters based on similarities.
</li>
<li>
Dimensionality Reduction: Techniques like Principal Component Analysis (PCA) reduce the complexity of data, making patterns more visible.
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
Goal: To discover hidden patterns or groupings in the data.
</li>
</ul>

<h3>The Common Thread: Algorithms and Statistics</h3>
<p>Both types of learning rely heavily on algorithms (step-by-step mathematical procedures) and statistical methods. These are not alien concepts but extensions of mathematics and statistics applied to data. The computer is essentially doing a lot of calculations and predictions based on the mathematical models it builds from the data.</p>

<h2>Visualizing a Supervised Learning Function</h2>
<p>Imagine you're dealing with a basic linear regression problem, which is a common type of supervised learning. Here's how you might visualize it:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Graph Setup:
<br />
X-Axis: Represents the input feature (e.g., the size of a house).<br />
Y-Axis: Represents the output or prediction (e.g., the price of the house).
</li>
<li>
Data Points:
<br />
Plot data points on this graph. Each point represents a known example from your dataset (e.g., a house of a certain size and its corresponding price).
</li>
<li>
The Learning Function:
</li>
Draw a line through these points. This line is your machine learning function. In linear regression, it's the "best fit" line that minimizes the distance (error) between itself and all the data points.
The equation of this line (like y = mx + b) is what the machine learning model has learned. Here, 'm' is the slope, and 'b' is the y-intercept.<br /><br />
<li>
Prediction:
</li>
To make a prediction, you input a new value of X (e.g., the size of a new house) and see where it hits the line on the graph. The corresponding Y value is your predicted price.</ul>
<h2>Tools to Create This Visualization:</h2>
<ul>
<li>
Software like Excel or Google Sheets: You can plot the data points and add a trendline.
</li>
<li>
Programming Languages: Python with libraries like Matplotlib or Seaborn is excellent for more complex data.
</li>
<li>
Online Graphing Tools: Websites like Desmos allow you to plot points and lines easily.
</li>
</ul>
<p>This visualization helps you see how the machine learning model (in this case, the line) is making predictions based on the input data. It’s a simple yet powerful way to understand the basics of supervised learning functions.
<br />
<br />
Now head over to my portfolio area where you can look at some examples of machine learning.  So far I have the facial recognition applet up and functioning.  This uses machine learning to look at your face and determine your mood (or moods).  More playground stuff with machine learning to come in the very near future (this week or next).  Check back frequently for portfolio updates.
<br />
<br />
Respectfully,
Adrian Hacker
<br />
<br />
p.s.
<br />
I just had Wanda read this article that I have written, and I can tell she is much more at ease. She isn’t a big fan of all the math and could really care less about all of that, but she can see that it isn’t alien technology that will usurp our humanity from us overnight.
<br />
<br /></p>

<p><a href="/portfolio-2">portfolio</a></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/bg/wandarug.jpg" alt="Wanda Relaxing In The Sun" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian Hacker</name></author><category term="Artificial Intelligence" /><category term="a.i." /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Wanda Won't A.I. Unofficially, this blog post is titled "Wanda Won't A.I." and it refers to my beautiful calico kitty who, if she were a person, I know would loathe the idea of artificial intelligence. Just as the robot vacuum has evolved to scare Wanda more thoroughly, so too has technology evolved to make people frightened. Enter: Artificial Intelligence. Perhaps the Matrix or Terminator 2 are plausible scenarios on the horizon people are wondering about. No, both A.I. and the robot vacuum are just two different facets of technology that is much older than people realize. And equally as harmless (mostly). Some interesting parallels exist in history around general fears of new technology.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Get the Most Out of this Website</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/inaugural-blog" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Get the Most Out of this Website" /><published>2023-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2023-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/inaugural-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/inaugural-blog"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my web presence and the inaugural blog entry. For the time being, this site is primarily a professional portfolio. I am pursuing the self-taught software engineer path because I have contributed significantly to the semiconductor industry, and now it's time for something new. Additionally, A.I. is extremely fascinating to me. I see numerous potential applications; A.I. could truly be the gateway to improving the quality of life for many.</p>

<p>A.I. also has the potential to lead humanity in the wrong direction with developments like deepfakes and the ability to spread false messaging convincingly. Could A.I. intersect with blockchain technology to create a public ledger of A.I. media creations? That's an intriguing idea worth exploring further.</p>

<p>In the portfolio section, you can view some of my A.I.-generated art or interact with live-hosted versions of various programming exercises I've completed. In the coming days, I'll be adding a chatbot to this site based on ChatGPT, capable of answering any questions you might have. I'm considering training it with specific knowledge about myself so users can ask various questions about me and receive accurate answers. Time will tell.</p>

<p>The blog section will feature important updates related to technology, tutorials, and other mostly professional topics. I encourage you to use the comment area but please keep it respectful.</p>

<p>These are the key subjects in my self-taught journey, for now:</p>
<ul>
    <li>HTML5 / CSS</li>
    <li>JavaScript</li>
    <li>Node JS</li>
    <li>React</li>
    <li>Docker</li>
    <li>Amazon Web Services</li>
    <li>Artificial Intelligence</li>
    <li>Some Python for web scraping and data visualization</li>
</ul>

<p>Feel free to reach out if you're moved to do so, interested in hiring me, seeking freelance services, or just generally curious about me.</p>

<p>Cheers,<br />
Adrian</p>]]></content><author><name>Adrian Hacker</name></author><category term="Tutorial" /><category term="tutorial" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my web presence and the inaugural blog entry. For the time being, this site is primarily a professional portfolio. I am pursuing the self-taught software engineer path because I have contributed significantly to the semiconductor industry, and now it's time for something new. Additionally, A.I. is extremely fascinating to me. I see numerous potential applications; A.I. could truly be the gateway to improving the quality of life for many.]]></summary></entry></feed>